<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sedimentology on Zoltán Sylvester</title>
    <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/tags/sedimentology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sedimentology on Zoltán Sylvester</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2018 Zoltan Sylvester</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://zsylvester.github.io/tags/sedimentology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring (de)compaction with Python</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/decompaction/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/decompaction/</guid>
      <description>All clastic sediments are subject to compaction (and reduction of porosity) as the result of increasingly tighter packing of grains under a thickening overburden. Decompaction - the estimation of the decompacted thickness of a rock column - is an important part of subsidence (or geohistory) analysis. The following exercise is loosely based on the excellent basin analysis textbook by Allen &amp;amp; Allen (2013), especially their Appendix 56.
Import stuff import numpy as np import matplotlib.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the diffusion equation with Python</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/diffusion_equation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/diffusion_equation/</guid>
      <description>Ever since I became interested in science, I started to have a vague idea that calculus, matrix algebra, partial differential equations, and numerical methods are all fundamental to the physical sciences and engineering and they are linked in some way to each other. The emphasis here is on the word vague; I have to admit that I had no clear, detailed understanding of how these links actually work. It seems like my formal education both in math and physics stopped just short of where everything would have nicely come together.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rivers through time, as seen in Landsat images</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/rivers_through_time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/rivers_through_time/</guid>
      <description>Thanks to the Landsat program and Google Earth Engine, it is possible now to explore how the surface of the Earth has been changing through the last thirty years or so. Besides the obvious issues of interest, like changes in vegetation, the spread of cities, and the melting of glaciers, it is also possible to look at how rivers change their courses through time. You have probably already seen the images of the migrating Ucayali River in Peru, for example here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring grain settling with Python</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/grain_settling/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/grain_settling/</guid>
      <description>Grain settling is one of the most important problems in sedimentology (and therefore sedimentary geology), as neither sediment transport nor deposition can be understood and modeled without knowing what is the settling velocity of a particle of a certain grain size. Very small grains, when submerged in water, have a mass small enough that they reach a terminal velocity before any turbulence develops. This is true for clay- and silt-sized particles settling in water, and for these grain size classes Stokes&amp;rsquo; Law can be used to calculate the settling velocity:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Salt and sediment: a brief history of ideas</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/salt_and_sediment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/salt_and_sediment/</guid>
      <description>Salty weirdness Salt is a weird kind of rock. At first sight, it behaves like most other rocks: if you pick up a piece, it is hard, it is heavy, and it breaks if hit with a hammer. But put it under stress for thousands of years, and salt will behave like a fluid: relatively small forces can cause it to flow toward less stressful surroundings. This often means it will try to find its way to the surface.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stretching the truth: vertical exaggeration of seismic data</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/vertical_exaggeration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/vertical_exaggeration/</guid>
      <description>If someone showed a photograph of the famous Cuernos massif (Torres del Paine National Park, Chile) like the one below, it would be - probably, hopefully - obvious to everybody that something is wrong with the picture. Our eyes and brains have seen enough mountain scenery that we intuitively know how steep is &amp;lsquo;steep&amp;rsquo; in alpine landscapes. The peaks in this photograph just look too extreme, too high if one takes into account their lateral extent.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>