<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Meandering on Zoltán Sylvester</title>
    <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/tags/meandering/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Meandering on Zoltán Sylvester</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.148.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://zsylvester.github.io/tags/meandering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Meandering streamflows across landscapes and scales: a review and discussion</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/meandering_book_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/meandering_book_intro/</guid>
      <description>This introductory chapter reviews the history of research on meandering streams and presents a compilation of data on meander morphology. Published in *Geological Society, London, Special Publications*, 2024.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of post-cutoff bend curvature on channel kinematics in meandering rivers: an example from the Trinity River, Texas, USA</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/trinity_cutoffs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/trinity_cutoffs/</guid>
      <description>This paper investigates the relationship between post-cutoff bend curvature and channel kinematics in meandering rivers using Trinity River data. Published in *Geological Society, London, Special Publications*, 2024.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giant meandering channel evolution, Campos deep-water salt basin, Brazil</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/campos_giant_channels/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/campos_giant_channels/</guid>
      <description>This paper analyzes the evolution of giant meandering submarine channels in the Campos Basin, Brazil, and their interaction with salt diapirs. Published in *Geosphere*, 2021.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autogenic translation and counter point bar deposition in meandering rivers</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/counter_point_bars_gsa_bull/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/counter_point_bars_gsa_bull/</guid>
      <description>This paper explores the development of counter point bars in meandering rivers through autogenic translation processes. Published in *GSA Bulletin*, 2021.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Point bars and counter point bars: Why is sediment deposited on the &#39;wrong&#39; side of a meander bend?</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/counter_point_bars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/counter_point_bars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The simplest definition of point bars is that they are sedimentary deposits forming on the inner, convex bank of river bends. [&amp;lsquo;Inner&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;convex&amp;rsquo; bank means that, looking toward the river, the bank is curving around you.] &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amadeus_William_Grabau&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Amadeus W. Grabau&lt;/a&gt;, an early &amp;lsquo;influencer&amp;rsquo; in stratigraphy and sedimentary geology, published a beautiful drawing of how meanders grow, point bars evolve, and oxbow lakes form, more than a hundred years ago:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;plot&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://zsylvester.github.io/img/grabau_meanders.png#center600&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=center&gt;*Diagram illustrating the development of meanders in a river. From Grabau (1920).*&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the relationship between meander‐bend curvature, sediment supply, and migration rates</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/donovan_et_al_jgr/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/donovan_et_al_jgr/</guid>
      <description>Published in *Journal of Geophysical Research: Earth Surface, v. 126, e2020JF006058*, 2021.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does river migration slow down in high-curvature bends?</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/curvature_migration_rate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/curvature_migration_rate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The answer, at least for seven rivers of the Amazon Basin, seems to be negative, as we try to demonstrate in &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubs.geoscienceworld.org/gsa/geology/article/568705/high-curvatures-drive-river-meandering&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a paper that was recently published in Geology&lt;/a&gt;. My coauthors are &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.ca/citations?user=KeTNzo0AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Paul Durkin&lt;/a&gt;, at the University of Manitoba, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.beg.utexas.edu/people/jacob-covault&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jake Covault&lt;/a&gt;, at the Bureau of Economic Geology, The University of Texas at Austin. In this blog post, I try to provide a bit more background to our paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is this an interesting result? After all, it makes sense that there is more outer bank erosion in sharper bends. Erosion is primarily a function of the shear stress exerted on the bank; and shear stress is high where the high-velocity core of the river gets close to the bank (because in this case flow velocity has to quickly decrease from a maximum to zero, and shear stress is a function of the rate of change in velocity). The high-velocity core gets pushed close to the bank if the centrifugal force is large; and the centrifugal force is directly proportional to curvature, 1/R (where R is the radius of curvature). In short, if we use the simplest, most pedestrian physical reasoning, we would expect that erosion, and therefore bank migration, are high in high-curvature bends. However, a lot of previous work on meandering rivers suggests that this is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the case.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High curvatures drive river meandering</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/curvature_and_migration_rate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/curvature_and_migration_rate/</guid>
      <description>Published in *Geology, v. 47, p. 263-266*, 2019.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latitudinal Changes in the Morphology of Submarine Channels: Reevaluating the Evidence for the Influence of the Coriolis Force</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/coriolis_and_submarine_channels/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/coriolis_and_submarine_channels/</guid>
      <description>Published in *SEPM Special Publication v. 108*, 2018.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid Adjustment of Submarine Channel Architecture To Changes In Sediment Supply</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/nigeria_rapid_adjustment/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/papers/nigeria_rapid_adjustment/</guid>
      <description>Published in *Journal of Sedimentary Research v. 85, p. 729-753*, 2015.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
