<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Zoltán Sylvester</title>
    <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Zoltán Sylvester</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.148.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://zsylvester.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Point bars and counter point bars: Why is sediment deposited on the &#39;wrong&#39; side of a meander bend?</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/counter_point_bars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/counter_point_bars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The simplest definition of point bars is that they are sedimentary deposits forming on the inner, convex bank of river bends. [&amp;lsquo;Inner&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;convex&amp;rsquo; bank means that, looking toward the river, the bank is curving around you.] &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amadeus_William_Grabau&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Amadeus W. Grabau&lt;/a&gt;, an early &amp;lsquo;influencer&amp;rsquo; in stratigraphy and sedimentary geology, published a beautiful drawing of how meanders grow, point bars evolve, and oxbow lakes form, more than a hundred years ago:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;plot&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://zsylvester.github.io/img/grabau_meanders.png#center600&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=center&gt;*Diagram illustrating the development of meanders in a river. From Grabau (1920).*&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does river migration slow down in high-curvature bends?</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/curvature_migration_rate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/curvature_migration_rate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The answer, at least for seven rivers of the Amazon Basin, seems to be negative, as we try to demonstrate in &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubs.geoscienceworld.org/gsa/geology/article/568705/high-curvatures-drive-river-meandering&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a paper that was recently published in Geology&lt;/a&gt;. My coauthors are &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.ca/citations?user=KeTNzo0AAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Paul Durkin&lt;/a&gt;, at the University of Manitoba, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.beg.utexas.edu/people/jacob-covault&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jake Covault&lt;/a&gt;, at the Bureau of Economic Geology, The University of Texas at Austin. In this blog post, I try to provide a bit more background to our paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is this an interesting result? After all, it makes sense that there is more outer bank erosion in sharper bends. Erosion is primarily a function of the shear stress exerted on the bank; and shear stress is high where the high-velocity core of the river gets close to the bank (because in this case flow velocity has to quickly decrease from a maximum to zero, and shear stress is a function of the rate of change in velocity). The high-velocity core gets pushed close to the bank if the centrifugal force is large; and the centrifugal force is directly proportional to curvature, 1/R (where R is the radius of curvature). In short, if we use the simplest, most pedestrian physical reasoning, we would expect that erosion, and therefore bank migration, are high in high-curvature bends. However, a lot of previous work on meandering rivers suggests that this is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the case.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stratal patterns in salt-withdrawal minibasins</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/stratal_patterns/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/stratal_patterns/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;These are animations that accompany our 2015 article on the stratigraphy of salt-withdrawal basins on the slope (Sylvester, Z., Cantelli, A., and Pirmez, C., 2015, &lt;a href=&#34;http://archives.datapages.com/data/bulletns/2015/06jun/BLTN14082/BLTN14082.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Stratigraphic evolution of intraslope minibasins: Insights from surface-based model: AAPG Bulletin, v. 99, no. 6, p. 1099–1129&lt;/a&gt;). We have used a simple model that investigates the interplay between subsidence and sedimentation and helps in the understanding of how stratal termination patterns relate to variations in sediment input and basin subsidence. Conventional sequence stratigraphy focuses on what is happening on the shelf and the shelf edge; and the origin of stratal patterns that characterize the typical &amp;lsquo;slug diagram&amp;rsquo; are not trivial to relate to the three main parameters that influence continental-margin stratigraphy: changes in sea level, sediment supply, and subsidence. Our minibasin model is simpler because (1) it only has two parameters: sediment supply and subsidence (the impact of sea level - if any - is included in the sediment supply curve); and (2) sedimentary layers are deposited horizontally during each time step. The basic idea is to investigate the geometries of a system that consists of a depression that deepens through time and sediment is deposited in it with a certain rate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring (de)compaction with Python</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/decompaction/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/decompaction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All clastic sediments are subject to compaction (and reduction of porosity) as the result of increasingly tighter packing of grains under a thickening overburden. Decompaction - the estimation of the decompacted thickness of a rock column - is an important part of subsidence (or geohistory) analysis. The following exercise is loosely based on the excellent basin analysis textbook by Allen &amp;amp; Allen (2013), especially their Appendix 56.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;import-stuff&#34;&gt;Import stuff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;background-color:#fff;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-Python&#34; data-lang=&#34;Python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#00a&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#0aa;text-decoration:underline&#34;&gt;numpy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#00a&#34;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#0aa;text-decoration:underline&#34;&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#00a&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#0aa;text-decoration:underline&#34;&gt;matplotlib.pyplot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#00a&#34;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#0aa;text-decoration:underline&#34;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#00a&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#0aa;text-decoration:underline&#34;&gt;functools&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#00a&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#0aa;text-decoration:underline&#34;&gt;scipy.optimize&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#00a&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; bisect
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;%matplotlib inline
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;%config InlineBackend.figure_format = &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a50&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;svg&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;plt.rcParams[&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a50&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;mathtext.fontset&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;] = &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a50&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;cm&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;posing-the-problem&#34;&gt;Posing the problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a sediment column of a certain lithology with its top at $y_1$ and its base at $y_2$, we are trying to find the thickness and average porosity of the same sediment column at a different depth (see figure below). We are going to set the new top $y_1&amp;rsquo;$ and work towards finding the new base $y_2&amp;rsquo;$.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the diffusion equation with Python</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/diffusion_equation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/diffusion_equation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since I became interested in science, I started to have a vague idea that calculus, matrix algebra, partial differential equations, and numerical methods are all fundamental to the physical sciences and engineering and they are linked in some way to each other. The emphasis here is on the word vague; I have to admit that I had no clear, detailed understanding of how these links actually work. It seems like my formal education both in math and physics stopped just short of where everything would have nicely come together. Papers that are really important in geomorphology, sedimentology or stratigraphy seemed impossible to read as soon as they started assuming that I knew quite a bit about convective acceleration, numerical schemes, boundary conditions, and Cholesky factorization. Because I didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rivers through time, as seen in Landsat images</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/rivers_through_time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/rivers_through_time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the Landsat program and Google Earth Engine, it is possible now to explore how the surface of the Earth has been changing through the last thirty years or so. Besides the obvious issues of interest, like changes in vegetation, the spread of cities, and the melting of glaciers, it is also possible to look at how rivers change their courses through time. You have probably already seen the images of the migrating Ucayali River in Peru, for example &lt;a href=&#34;https://earthengine.google.org/#timelapse/v=-7.24496,-75.17632,10.567,latLng&amp;amp;amp;t=1.03&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This river is changing its course with an impressive speed; many – probably most – other rivers don’t show much obvious change during the same 30-year period. What determines the meander migration rate of rivers is an interesting question in fluvial geomorphology.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring grain settling with Python</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/grain_settling/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/grain_settling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Grain settling is one of the most important problems in sedimentology (and therefore sedimentary geology), as neither sediment transport nor deposition can be understood and modeled without knowing what is the settling velocity of a particle of a certain grain size. Very small grains, when submerged in water, have a mass small enough that they reach a terminal velocity before any turbulence develops. This is true for clay- and silt-sized particles settling in water, and for these grain size classes Stokes&amp;rsquo; Law can be used to calculate the settling velocity:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Salt and sediment: a brief history of ideas</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/salt_and_sediment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/salt_and_sediment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;salty-weirdness&#34;&gt;Salty weirdness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salt is a weird kind of rock. At first sight, it behaves like most other rocks: if you pick up a piece, it is hard, it is heavy, and it breaks if hit with a hammer. But put it under stress for thousands of years, and salt will behave like a fluid: relatively small forces can cause it to flow toward less stressful surroundings. This often means it will try to find its way to the surface.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stretching the truth: vertical exaggeration of seismic data</title>
      <link>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/vertical_exaggeration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zsylvester.github.io/post/vertical_exaggeration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If someone showed a photograph of the famous Cuernos massif (Torres del Paine National Park, Chile) like the one below, it would be - probably, hopefully - obvious to everybody that something is wrong with the picture. Our eyes and brains have seen enough mountain scenery that we intuitively know how steep is &amp;lsquo;steep&amp;rsquo; in alpine landscapes. The peaks in this photograph just look too extreme, too high if one takes into account their lateral extent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
